<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>VicAI Blog</title>
  <subtitle>Advancing AI at Victoria University of Wellington</subtitle>
  <link href="https://vicai.org.nz/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://vicai.org.nz/"/>
  <updated>2026-02-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://vicai.org.nz/</id>
  <author>
    <name>VicAI</name>
    <email>contact@vicai.org.nz</email>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>VicAI Hackathon 2026: Build Something That Matters</title>
    <link href="https://vicai.org.nz/blog/hackathon-2026/"/>
    <updated>2026-02-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://vicai.org.nz/blog/hackathon-2026/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re running our first ever hackathon, and we want you there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When:&lt;/strong&gt; April 12-13, 2026 (Saturday-Sunday)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where:&lt;/strong&gt; The Hub, Kelburn Campus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teams:&lt;/strong&gt; 2-4 people (we&#39;ll help you find a team if you don&#39;t have one)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost:&lt;/strong&gt; Free. Food and drinks provided.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prizes:&lt;/strong&gt; Sponsored by our industry partners&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The theme: AI for Aotearoa&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re not interested in generic chatbot demos. We want projects that address real problems in Aotearoa New Zealand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some directions to consider:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Te reo Maori language technology&lt;/strong&gt; — tools that support and revitalise te reo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Environmental monitoring&lt;/strong&gt; — AI for conservation, biosecurity, or climate adaptation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Public service delivery&lt;/strong&gt; — making government services more accessible and fair&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Healthcare access&lt;/strong&gt; — supporting rural and underserved communities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Education&lt;/strong&gt; — tools that help New Zealand students learn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&#39;re free to interpret the theme broadly. The only requirement is that your project should be built with New Zealand in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Who should enter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone. Seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don&#39;t need to be a CS student. You don&#39;t need to know machine learning. The best hackathon teams have a mix of skills — coders, designers, writers, domain experts, and people who are good at asking the right questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve never been to a hackathon before, this is a great first one. We&#39;ll have mentors on hand throughout the weekend, and we&#39;ll run a quick &amp;quot;hackathon 101&amp;quot; session at the start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What we&#39;re looking for&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judging will be based on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impact&lt;/strong&gt; — Does this solve a real problem for real people in NZ?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creativity&lt;/strong&gt; — Is the approach original and thoughtful?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Execution&lt;/strong&gt; — Does the prototype work? Is it well-presented?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Responsibility&lt;/strong&gt; — Have the team considered potential risks, biases, or ethical issues?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that we specifically include &amp;quot;responsibility&amp;quot; as a judging criterion. We believe building responsibly is part of building well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Register&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Registrations are open now. &lt;a href=&quot;https://vicai.org.nz/events/&quot;&gt;Sign up on our events page&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://vicai.org.nz/join/&quot;&gt;join VicAI&lt;/a&gt; if you haven&#39;t already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See you in April.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why Every VUW Student Should Care About AI Safety</title>
    <link href="https://vicai.org.nz/blog/ai-safety-nz/"/>
    <updated>2026-02-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://vicai.org.nz/blog/ai-safety-nz/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Artificial intelligence is no longer a niche topic confined to computer science lecture halls. It&#39;s in our phones, our hospitals, our courts, and our classrooms. Large language models write essays, generate code, and summarise legal documents. Computer vision systems monitor traffic, screen medical images, and assess insurance claims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, most of us — including the people building these systems — are only beginning to grapple with what it means for AI to fail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What do we mean by AI safety?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI safety is a broad field, but at its core it asks a simple question: &lt;strong&gt;how do we make sure AI systems do what we actually want them to do, without causing harm?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This covers a wide range of concerns:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alignment&lt;/strong&gt;: Does the AI&#39;s behaviour match human intentions?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Robustness&lt;/strong&gt;: Does it work reliably across different conditions, or does it break in unexpected ways?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fairness&lt;/strong&gt;: Does it treat different groups of people equitably?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transparency&lt;/strong&gt;: Can we understand why it made a particular decision?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Misuse&lt;/strong&gt;: Could someone use this system to cause deliberate harm?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These aren&#39;t hypothetical questions. They&#39;re playing out right now in hiring algorithms that discriminate, content recommendation systems that amplify misinformation, and autonomous vehicles that struggle with edge cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why does this matter in Aotearoa?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New Zealand has a unique opportunity — and responsibility — when it comes to AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our public sector is actively adopting AI tools. Stats NZ, ACC, MSD, and other agencies are exploring machine learning for decision-making. The question isn&#39;t whether AI will be used in government — it&#39;s how.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in Aotearoa, that &amp;quot;how&amp;quot; has particular weight. Any AI system operating here needs to reckon with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Te Tiriti o Waitangi&lt;/strong&gt; and the obligations it creates around partnership, protection, and participation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maori data sovereignty&lt;/strong&gt; — the principle that Maori data should be governed by Maori, and that indigenous knowledge systems must not be extracted or exploited by AI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The small population problem&lt;/strong&gt; — machine learning models trained on global datasets may not reflect the realities of a country of 5 million people with distinct demographics and cultural context&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These aren&#39;t edge cases. They&#39;re central questions for anyone deploying AI in this country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;You don&#39;t need to be a coder to care&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest misconceptions about AI safety is that it&#39;s a purely technical problem. It&#39;s not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, alignment research involves deep mathematics and computer science. But the broader challenge of AI governance — deciding what we want AI to do, who gets to make those decisions, and how we hold systems accountable — requires perspectives from law, philosophy, political science, public policy, indigenous studies, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re studying law at VUW, you should understand how AI is used in criminal justice and what it means for the right to a fair trial. If you&#39;re studying public policy, you should understand how algorithmic decision-making changes the relationship between citizens and the state. If you&#39;re studying design, you should understand how interfaces shape people&#39;s understanding of AI outputs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI safety is everyone&#39;s business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What VicAI is doing about it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our Safety &amp;amp; Governance team runs reading groups, panel discussions, and research projects focused on responsible AI in Aotearoa. We&#39;ve hosted discussions on Maori data sovereignty, algorithmic accountability in government, and the ethics of generative AI in education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don&#39;t pretend to have all the answers. But we believe that students — from every faculty — should be part of the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best time to think about AI safety was ten years ago. The second best time is now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this resonates with you, &lt;a href=&quot;https://vicai.org.nz/join/&quot;&gt;join VicAI&lt;/a&gt; and get involved. You don&#39;t need to write code. You just need to care.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Workshop Recap: Building Your First LLM Application</title>
    <link href="https://vicai.org.nz/blog/llm-workshop-recap/"/>
    <updated>2026-01-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://vicai.org.nz/blog/llm-workshop-recap/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last Saturday, 40 students packed into Cotton Building CO350 for our &amp;quot;Build Your First LLM App&amp;quot; workshop. The energy was brilliant. Half the room had never used an API before. By the end of the session, every team had a working prototype.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s what we covered and what we learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The format&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We structured the workshop in three phases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concept&lt;/strong&gt; (45 min) — What are LLMs, how do APIs work, what is prompt engineering?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build&lt;/strong&gt; (90 min) — Teams of 2-3 building a working app using the Anthropic API&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Show &amp;amp; Tell&lt;/strong&gt; (30 min) — Each team demos their creation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No slides longer than 5 minutes. No lectures. Just enough context to get started, then hands on keyboards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What people built&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The projects were genuinely creative. A few highlights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Te Reo helper&lt;/strong&gt; — A conversational app that helps English speakers practice basic te reo Maori phrases, with pronunciation tips and cultural context&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COMP102 study buddy&lt;/strong&gt; — An app that explains introductory programming concepts, tuned to the VUW COMP102 curriculum&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flatting advisor&lt;/strong&gt; — Answers questions about tenants&#39; rights in NZ, pulling from the Residential Tenancies Act&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research paper summariser&lt;/strong&gt; — Takes an academic paper abstract and produces a one-paragraph summary aimed at a general audience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Key takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prompt engineering is more important than code.&lt;/strong&gt; The teams that spent the most time crafting their system prompts — being specific about tone, context, and constraints — got the best results. The actual API integration code was less than 20 lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Guardrails matter from day one.&lt;/strong&gt; One team&#39;s flatting advisor initially gave confident but wrong legal advice. Adding explicit instructions like &amp;quot;if you&#39;re not sure, say so and recommend contacting Tenancy Services&amp;quot; dramatically improved the output. This is AI safety in practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You don&#39;t need a CS degree to build with AI.&lt;/strong&gt; Several teams included students from non-technical backgrounds who contributed enormously — writing prompts, designing the user experience, and stress-testing the output for errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you missed the workshop and want to catch up, here are the resources we used:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anthropic API docs and getting started guide&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our workshop starter template (available on our GitHub)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The prompt engineering guide from Anthropic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Next workshop&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our next hands-on session is &lt;strong&gt;Computer Vision with PyTorch&lt;/strong&gt; on April 19th. This one&#39;s more technical — intermediate Python knowledge is recommended. &lt;a href=&quot;https://vicai.org.nz/events/&quot;&gt;Check the events page&lt;/a&gt; for details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to suggest a workshop topic or help run one, reach out to the Education team through our &lt;a href=&quot;https://vicai.org.nz/contact/&quot;&gt;contact page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Careers in AI: The New Zealand Landscape</title>
    <link href="https://vicai.org.nz/blog/careers-in-ai-nz/"/>
    <updated>2026-01-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://vicai.org.nz/blog/careers-in-ai-nz/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When people think about AI careers, they usually think Silicon Valley. But Aotearoa has a growing AI ecosystem that&#39;s worth paying attention to — especially if you want to build technology that serves a small, diverse, and community-minded country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We surveyed the landscape. Here&#39;s what we found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wellington: Government and public sector&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wellington is the centre of New Zealand&#39;s public sector, and government agencies are increasingly adopting AI. Stats NZ, the Ministry of Social Development, ACC, and the Department of Internal Affairs are all exploring or deploying machine learning tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roles in this space often combine technical skills with policy understanding. If you&#39;re interested in AI governance, algorithmic accountability, or responsible AI deployment, Wellington is arguably the most interesting place in the country to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key organisations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stats NZ&lt;/strong&gt; — data science and statistical modelling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NZQA&lt;/strong&gt; — exploring AI for credential assessment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MBIE&lt;/strong&gt; — innovation policy and AI strategy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Various Crown Research Institutes&lt;/strong&gt; — applied AI research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Auckland: Startups and scale-ups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Auckland has the largest concentration of AI startups in New Zealand. Companies like &lt;strong&gt;Soul Machines&lt;/strong&gt; (autonomous animation), &lt;strong&gt;Imagr&lt;/strong&gt; (computer vision for retail), and &lt;strong&gt;Xtended AI&lt;/strong&gt; are building products for global markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The startup ecosystem is smaller than overseas, but that&#39;s not necessarily a disadvantage. In a small company, you&#39;re closer to the problem, you ship faster, and you learn across the stack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Christchurch and beyond&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t overlook the regions. The University of Canterbury has strong AI research programmes. AgriTech companies across Canterbury and the Waikato are using ML for precision agriculture. And remote work means geography matters less than it used to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What employers want&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on conversations with hiring managers at our Industry Night events, here&#39;s what NZ employers look for in AI roles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python proficiency&lt;/strong&gt; — still the lingua franca of ML&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understanding of ML fundamentals&lt;/strong&gt; — not just library calls, but understanding why algorithms work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Communication skills&lt;/strong&gt; — can you explain your model to a non-technical stakeholder?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Domain knowledge&lt;/strong&gt; — understanding the problem space matters as much as the algorithms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ethics awareness&lt;/strong&gt; — increasingly, companies want people who can think about the societal impact of what they&#39;re building&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What you can do now&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re a VUW student thinking about AI careers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Join VicAI&lt;/strong&gt; — our events connect you directly with industry professionals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do a summer research project&lt;/strong&gt; — VUW&#39;s School of ECS runs summer scholarships&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build a portfolio&lt;/strong&gt; — GitHub projects, blog posts, and workshop contributions all count&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learn the fundamentals&lt;/strong&gt; — COMP309 (Machine Learning) and SWEN432 (Advanced Data Engineering) are solid starting points&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Think broadly&lt;/strong&gt; — AI careers aren&#39;t just for CS graduates. Data analysts, policy advisors, UX designers, and ethicists are all needed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AI job market in NZ is small but growing fast. The students who start building skills and connections now will be well positioned.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
